<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A summarie account of Mr. Iohn Dury's former and latter negotiation for the procuring of the true gospell peace with Christian moderation and charitable unity amongst the Protestant churches and academies.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209716</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11209716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204906</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21493)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204906)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1440:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A summarie account of Mr. Iohn Dury's former and latter negotiation for the procuring of the true gospell peace with Christian moderation and charitable unity amongst the Protestant churches and academies.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</term>
               <term>Christian union.</term>
               <term>Church history --  Modern period, 1500-</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204906:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204906:1"/>
            <p>A SUMMARIE ACCOUNT OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Iohn Dury's FORMER and LATTER NEGOTIATION: For the procuring of true Goſpell Peace, with Chriſtian Moderation and Charitable Unity amongſt the Proteſtant Churches, and Academies.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ABORE ET CONSTANTIA</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Plantin Press</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, in the year 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:204906:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204906:2"/>
            <head>A SUMMARY ACCOUNT OF Maſter <hi>JOHN D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RYE</hi>'s former and latter NEGOTIATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen in the yeer 1628. <hi>John Dury</hi> was in <hi>Pruſſia</hi> Miniſter to the Engliſh Company of Merchants reſiding at <hi>Elbing,</hi> he was ſent unto,<note place="margin">The firſt occaſion of this work was at <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing.</hi>
               </note> dealt withal, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1628</label> and moved by Dr. <hi>Godeman</hi> a wiſe, godly, and learned man, one of the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, and Judge of his high Court in thoſe parts, to ſecond him in a buſineſs of Eccleſiaſticall Unity amongſt Proteſtants, which he ſaid his King and Maſter would be glad to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. So good a motion being readily entertained, it came to paſs afterward, when Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> was ſent Ambaſſadour Extraordinary by his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durre</hi>'s being at <hi>Elbing.</hi>
               </note> to agree the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Polonians</hi> (which alſo he did ſucceſsfully perform) that both Doctor <hi>Godeman</hi> and Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did make him throughly acquainted with all the paſſages of their Negotiation. Whereupon he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that generous diſpoſition, which did lead him to favour all good endeavours of a publick nature, did very
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204906:3"/>willingly aſſiſt them with Counſel, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1629</label> and at Maſter <hi>Duryes</hi> intreaty, conferred with the Lord Chancellor <hi>Oxenſtiern,</hi> to ſee how far he would ſhew himſelf in the buſineſs, and what courſe might be reſolved upon to proceed joyntly to the effect thereof. The Lord Chancellor manifeſted a good liking to the work, and promiſed to my Lord Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to joyn effectually therein towards his King, and the Lutheran Clergy of his beſt acquaintance. Upon this ground, my Lord Ambaſſadour encouraged Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> to proceed; and when his Lordſhip was gone into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Lord Chancellor ſent for him, heard his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Propoſals, conferred with him about the ſame, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified his willingneſs to give aſſiſtance thereunto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> to give him information of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the work in time to come; ſo he went from <hi>Elbing</hi> into <hi>England</hi> in the year 1630.<note place="margin">England.</note> Chiefly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1630</label> becauſe his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation at <hi>Elbing</hi> was diſſolved, by reaſon of the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences which war had brought upon the Trade in that place: and becauſe Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> had promiſed to move the chief Prelates in <hi>England</hi> to aſſiſt him in the work of pacification.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Being then arrived there, he firſt acquainted his moſt familiar friends of the Clergie with his purpoſe, and ſhewed them ſome Declarations written by the chief Preachers of <hi>Dantzigh</hi> to make it appear, that they were not onely ready to joyn in ſuch a Negotiation, but alſo deſirous and in hope that the Divines in <hi>England</hi> would in like manner concur; which being done, he came to Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> who was mindfull of his promiſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came every way as good as his word towards him. For he recommended the buſineſs towards the King, who was pleaſed to refer the conſideration of the matter to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> that they ſhould hear Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> and declare their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his Propoſals. This was done accordingly; and he was commanded to write unto the Divines of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and to the Lord Chancellor <hi>Oxenſtiern,</hi> to teſtifie firſt the good inclination, and reſolution which the Clergie of <hi>England</hi> had, to co-operate in due time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204906:3"/>ſo good a work. Secondly, That their Counſell for the preſent was onely this, that to prepare a way for future Treaties, the Magiſtrates of both ſides ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> railing diſputes in the Pulpit, and put down the names of partiality, ſo far as could be done, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any publick Diſputes to be fomented about matters of Ceremony in the form of publick Worſhip.</p>
            <p>This he did, and after a good ſpace, when news came, that the Proteſtant Princes in <hi>Germany</hi> had leagued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together for their mutuall defence, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1631</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being in <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </note> and that an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable conference of their Divines had been holden with good ſucceſs at <hi>Leipzigh</hi> to compoſe their differences in Religion, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> was permitted to go into <hi>Germany,</hi> that he might ſee how the Divines of all ſides might be diſpoſed towards a Conjunction of Councels, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the Work.</p>
            <p>To make a way for this purpoſe, he had before-hand by the means of Sir <hi>James Spenſe</hi> Lord of <hi>Oreholm,</hi> and Generall to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation in the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army, given notice to his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> what his aim was in the buſineſs of Reconcilement, and how it might be effected: Therefore when he came in the year 1631. into <hi>Germany,</hi> he found the King ſomewhat prepared, whom ſoon after the Battell fought at <hi>Leipzigh,</hi> he ſpoke withall at <hi>Wirtſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> His Majeſty was pleaſed to give him large audience,<note place="margin">At <hi>Wirtſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </note> and by conference received full information of all thoſe deliberations, and particular waies, whereby the Work could be proſecuted; of which, the Summary reſolution whereunto his Majeſty gave aſſent, was this: That the Counſel given by the Prelates of <hi>England</hi> was to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, for the inhibition of Diſputes and partial names: and that as Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did intend to labour with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Reformed ſide to diſpoſe them, to joyn una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly in the means and waies of amity, ſo his Majeſty would recommend the ſame endeavours to be undertaken by ſome Divines of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſide, who ſhould in like manner work upon the reſt of their own party, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when a fit preparation ſhould be found on both
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204906:4"/>ſides, then His Majeſty did offer to give unto Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> his Letters of publick recommendation towards the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Germany,</hi> and chiefly towards the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg,</hi> and <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> that with his and their concurrence, and the help of forrain Divines, the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might be brought to a ſolemn concluſion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1632</label> This fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable reſolution being taken, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> dealt firſt with the Divines of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> then with thoſe of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> and of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and of <hi>Deuxpont,</hi> and of the <hi>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraw,</hi> till he heard the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was dead; which evil news, although they made a ſtop in ſome part of his reſolutions, yet they made him not leave the ſame, but altering a little his courſe, he procured from all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Divines certain Letters and Declarations, whereof ſome were inſcribed to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> ſome joyntly to him and to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> whereby they ſhewed their ſerious intention to labour for unity, with a deſire to be aſſiſted by the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whiles this was a doing,<note place="margin">At <hi>Heil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Robert Anſtruther</hi> arrived as Extraordinary Ambaſſadour from his Majeſty to the Princes of <hi>Germany.</hi> With him Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> (having now gained the conſent of ſome of the chief reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in thoſe parts, and thinking it fit to deal with the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſide alſo) went to the meeting of the Proteſtant States, which was appointed at <hi>Heilebron,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1633</label> to frame an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall League. There he made uſe of ſome <hi>Lutheran</hi> Stateſmen to inſinuate to the Divines of that ſide certain Propoſitions, which made known unto them his purpoſe. This firſt motion was not without effect towards many,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi>
               </note> and chiefly towards thoſe of <hi>Strasburg</hi> and <hi>Norimberg,</hi> and ſome in the land of <hi>Wurtenburg.</hi> The meeting being ended, and the League framed at <hi>Heilebrone,</hi> he returned from thence towards the quarters of <hi>Franckfort,</hi> and dealt with two ſuperintendents, Doctor <hi>Dunner</hi> who was ſet over <hi>Mentz</hi> by the Lord Chancellor of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſering</hi> who had the inſpection of <hi>Darmſtat,</hi> and with the Senior Paſtor of the City of <hi>Franckfort,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tettel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach.</hi> All theſe were brought to recommend the Work
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204906:4"/>unto their Brethren, and in the mean time the Churches at <hi>Paris, Geneva, Metts,</hi> and the Univerſity of <hi>Sedan,</hi> ſent their anſwers (for Letters formerly had been written to them) wherein they aſſiſted Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> with Counſell. Some alſo of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſide declared in like manner a forward zeal and inclination to the work, by certain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations imparted to that effect unto him. Therefore when a larger opportunity to work more effectually upon all, was offered by another meeting of the Proteſtant States, which was appointed at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> he thought good to make his intention known unto the convocated Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and deſired their aſſiſtance to further the ſame; whereupon a reſolution was taken to this effect:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas Mr.</hi> Dury <hi>having deſired of the Confederate Evangelicall States, permiſſion to treat with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Paſtors of their Churches, concerning the means of Peace Eccleſiaſtical; Although the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours then preſent had not gotten any particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions concerning this matter from their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals: yet nevertheleſs their opinion was, that if the Lord Chancellor</hi> Oxenſtiern <hi>would by his authority ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce this matter, that their Masters who wiſh from their hearts for this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, will be ſo much the more ready with all their endeavours to give aſſistance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, according to the beginning made at the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence held at</hi> Leipzigh, <hi>whereunto the Lords States, who are now preſent, in like manner unanimouſly do</hi> compromitte.</p>
            <p>Having gotten this approbation of the Work, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation thereof by the States unto the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor; and being much incouraged by the private pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of aſſiſtance, which the ſeverall Ambaſſadours from all parts made unto him, he thought fit to write Letters to all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Univerſities, and to thoſe of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:204906:5"/>to acquaint them with his purpoſe of ſeeking Unity in matters of Religion. Which being done, when afterward another meeting was in agitation to be held at <hi>Erfurt</hi> in the Spring,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Frankfort.</hi>
               </note> he thought it fit (becauſe he was minded to return in the mean time for <hi>England</hi>) to move the Ambaſſadours of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1633</label> of <hi>Deuxpont,</hi> and of <hi>Heſſen;</hi> in caſe that any meeting ſhould be held before he could come back again, that they would be pleaſed to frame amongſt themſelves ſome courſe, how this matter might be proſecuted thereat; leſt ſo good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings might be without effect. They conſented to this motion, and met to conſult about the matter. The effect of their reſolution was this, That they would labour, in caſe a meeting ſhould be called, to cauſe inſert in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters invitatory this Clauſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That every one of the Princes would be pleaſed to bring along with him a Divine or two, inſtructed and authorized by his Churches, to give advice about the means of procuring <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and compoſing differences in Religion; and if the States ſhould not meet there, that nevertheleſs in time and place convenient, ſome particular Convocation of their own Divines ſhould be brought to paſs, wherein theſe two Points ſhould be put to deliberation;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Whether, yea, or no, the Acts of the laſt Conference held at</hi> Leipzigh, <hi>ſhould not be received by all the Churches, ſo far as they contain an agreement of the Articles of the Confeſſion of</hi> Ausburg?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Whether, yea, or no, the heads where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a diſagreement may be yet remaining in that Conference, cannot admit of a Reconciliation;</hi> if yea, what that Reconciliation may be; if no, then it is to be inquired, whether or no, thoſe remaining dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of opinion, be of ſuch importance, that by reaſon of the ſame, a Schiſme ſhould be upheld betwixt the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204906:5"/>
            <p>Theſe things the Ambaſſadour, and Chancellor of the Elector of <hi>Brandinburg</hi> did take upon him to ſet forward by the means of his Prince.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note> So then Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went through <hi>Holland</hi> (where he ſaluted the chief Divines to whom he had written out of <hi>Franckfort,</hi> and ſome others of his acquaintance) and arrived at <hi>London</hi> about the end of the yeer, 1633. There he found D. <hi>Laud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> Archbiſhop of <hi>Ganterbury</hi> in his Predeceſſors place. Therefore the Letters and Declarations of forraign Churches and Divines were preſented to him, with a brief Narrative of more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proceedings. All was well liked, and a reſolution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, that Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſhould proceed, and return again into <hi>Germany;</hi> which that he might do with greater advantage to the work, he dealt before his departure with Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Excester,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Davenant</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who gave him certain Theologicall Declarations for the advancement of his purpoſe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1634</label> To which effect, he alſo wrote into <hi>Ireland</hi> to Dr. <hi>Uſher,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagb,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to the two Biſhops of <hi>Kilmore</hi> and <hi>Ardach,</hi> who in like manner did afterward joyntly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him with their advices to the ſame end. In the mean time Letters were ſent alſo from <hi>Helvetia,</hi> and from <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimberg,</hi> giving ſuch teſtimony of concurrence, as were fit to encourage him to proceed. For which cauſe alſo when he was ready to go back again into <hi>Germany,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> gave him in anſwer to the Letters which he had brought from the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtants of both ſides, two Letters, the one to be communicated unto the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the other unto the <hi>Lutheran</hi> party, wherein he did acknowledge the receit of their Letters, and moving them to proceed in the good purpoſe which they had underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he promiſed in due time his further co-operation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. With theſe Declarations, together with a Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory Letter unto Sir <hi>Rob. Anſtruther,</hi> who was then Ambaſſadour for his Majeſty in <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> At <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </note> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Hamburg,</hi> where he found Sir <hi>Robert</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a new Commiſſion to go for <hi>Frankfort;</hi> and whilſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204906:6"/>his Lordſhip ſtayed,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi>
               </note> he took occaſion to acquaint the chief Divines of that City in their Conſiſtoriall meeting, with his Negotiation; who having promiſed to joyn en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, he went from thence towards <hi>Franckfort,</hi> to a great and ſolemn meeting of the Proteſtant States, where he arrived in my Lord Ambaſſadours company in <hi>June,</hi> 1634. There he dealt in particular, firſt with his beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and then made a Propoſition in generall to the Aſſembly; thereupon the States were moved to depute out of every Colledge ſome, to take his buſineſs into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. Theſe came together, gave Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, received informations of the circumſtances of this Work, and peruſed ſeverall declaratory Writings, which divers Univerſities and Divines of both ſides in <hi>Germany,</hi> as alſo out of <hi>Germany</hi> in forraign Churches, as <hi>England, France, Helvetia,</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> had given to him, which moved them to take the matter into ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and make a Decree, whereof the heads are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That Maſter</hi> Dury <hi>having been heard by a ſolemn Committee, and the Writs which he produced, taken into conſideration by the reſt of the States, all of them with unanimous conſent, did judge his Work moſt laudable, moſt acceptable to God, and moſt neceſſary and uſefull to his Church; yet ſeeing it was of great and weighty conſequence, and that many of the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours had not received any Inſtructions thereabout from their Masters, therefore no final reſolution could be taken by them at that preſent, but that they would faithfully relate and recommend the buſineſs unto their Maſters, to bring them to ſome effectual reſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That others who had received Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from their Principals about the matter, had propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two ways of proceeding in the Work; ſome thought it expedient, that the manner of proceeding which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204906:6"/>Maſter</hi> Dury <hi>had ſuggeſted unto the States,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhould be followed in bringing a Conference of peaceable Divines to paſs, that a fundamental agreement in points neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for ſalvation, according to the example of the Conference held at</hi> Leipzigh <hi>might be ſetled; And that to this effect, the States of the four <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Circles ſhould give up unto the Prince Elector</hi> Palatine, <hi>their more particular advices towards the furthering of the matter; and that the Declarations of the two</hi> Saxon <hi>Circles ſhould be given up to the Elector of</hi> Saxony <hi>and</hi> Brandinburg, <hi>who then ſhould agree amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerning the time and place of a Meeting, which might be named unto the reſt, and afterwards invitatory Letters ſhould be ſent to forraign States and Princes, to move them to ſend thither alſo ſome of their Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That others thought it no leſs expedient to proceed thus; namely, that the Electors of</hi> Saxony <hi>and</hi> Brandinburg <hi>ſhould be intreated by the States, then met together, to reaſſume the amiable Conference which was begun three yeers ago, betwixt their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and thoſe of</hi> Caſſell; <hi>and to this effect, that (if not ſooner, at leaſt then) when the Treaties of Peace <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſhould be ſet on foot, a meeting ſhould be appointed, whereunto peaceable Divines on both ſides, both within and out of the Empire, ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: In which meeting this ſhould chiefly be aimed at, That an agreement ſhould be made in a common Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, containing all the Fundamentals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion neceſſary for Salvation, ſetting other points of Scholaſticall diſpute aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That the Ambaſſadours who had no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions did promiſe to relate unto their Principals
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204906:7"/>theſe advices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Frankfort.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and procure fit reſolutions thereupon, which ſhould be ſent unto the Civil Electors, profeſſing the Protestant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Moreover, that it was fully conſented unto by ſome, and by ſome taken</hi> ad referendum, <hi>that in the mean time all Chriſtian moderation was to be uſed on both ſides, as well in preaching, as in writing; leſt if this was not done, ſome hinderance might befall unto their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and being done by this means, the Civil Peace alſo might ſo much the more be advanced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>That Prayers were to be conceived in the Churches of both ſides, to intreat Almighty God to bleſs theſe attempts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was made an Act the fourteenth day of <hi>September,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sept."/> 1634. To which the ſeal of thoſe which had the direction of the meeting was applied, and all the chief hands did ſubſcribe it.</p>
            <p>Of this Act, the Original ſealed and ſubſcribed, was given to Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> to enable him to teſtifie authentical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to other Churches, the reſolution of the Proteſtant States, that thereby all well-willers unto the work might be encouraged to continue in ſetting it forward. Upon this ground he went again towards <hi>England</hi> through the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the <hi>Low Countreys</hi>
               </note> where he informed the Divines of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and the Deputies of the Provincial Synods, of things paſt at <hi>Franckfort</hi> and elſewhere in theſe conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, obliging them thereby to take the matter to heart. And when he arrived into <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">England.</note> the Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bnry</hi> being informed of all matters, did by Sir <hi>Thomas Roes</hi> procurement recommend him to the King, who was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in taking more particular notice of his perſon and work, then in former time, to permit him ſtill to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.<note place="margin">Holland.</note> To which effect he went over again into <hi>Holland,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1635</label> with his Majeſties Letters of ſafe Conduct, with a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial from the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> bearing witneſs that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204906:7"/>Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had acquainted him with the ſucceſſe of his proceedings,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note> that he went again out of <hi>England</hi> to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame buſineſs, not onely with his knowledge, but alſo with his approbation, and aſſurance that he would be ready in due time, to advance ſuch holy deſires of Peace. He had alſo private Letters from Doctor <hi>Davenant</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> to ſome of the chief Divines of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> to move them to concur more effectually in theſe endeavours, then they had formerly done. Moreover, he had Letters from the Ambaſſadour of the Lords States of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> reſiding at <hi>London,</hi> unto the States both of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand.</hi> Thus he ſet forth, and arrived at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> the yeer 1635. There he dealt firſt with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> to induce them to recommend theſe thoughts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Provincial Synod which was then begun. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he went to thoſe of <hi>Zealand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>Zealand</hi>
               </note> and appeared in their Claſſical meetings held at <hi>Walcheren, Zirickzee, Tolen</hi> and <hi>Goes,</hi> then he dealt with the Univerſity of <hi>Leyden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leyden.</note> and the Synods as they came in order; namely, with that of <hi>North-Holland,</hi> and of <hi>Utrecht,</hi> and with the French Synod in thoſe parts, from which Declarations were obtained, fit for the advancement of his purpoſe: When he had thus far proceeded in <hi>Holland,</hi> and found that evil-affected mindes towards Peace, raiſed ungrounded ſurmiſes againſt him, to ſtop the good inclinations of impartiall men, he uſed means to clear mens judgements, by cauſing ſome things to be printed for the better information of all. And having underſtood that the Lord Chancellor <hi>Oxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiern</hi> was to go from <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Sweden,</hi> where he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that his Lordſhip would do more then in <hi>Germany</hi> he was able to do for the work of Peace; at the perſwaſion of ſome friends, he took a journey thitherward, where he arrived in <hi>June,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1636</label> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1636.<note place="margin">In <hi>Sweden.</hi>
               </note> Nor was he altogether diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of his expectation. For the Lord Chancellor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither favoured his work; and although his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were flow, yet much reality was found in them. For when a reſolution was taken to permit Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> to treat
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204906:8"/>with the Divines of that Kingdome,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
               </note> four places were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Stockholm, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bſall, Weſteroſe,</hi> and <hi>Strengneſe,</hi> to which he might addreſs himſelf particularly, and lay open his intention, having therefore firſt dealt with thoſe of <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm,</hi> he had the Lord Chancellors Letters to make way for him at the other places,<note place="margin">Upſall.</note> of which the Univerſity of <hi>Ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall</hi> was the chief. There he had conference both Collegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and ſeverally with the Profeſſors of Divinity, who gave full aſſent unto his deſires, and ſet down theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, upon which they were ready to agree and joyne with the Reformed ſide.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That a full agreement ſhould be made in all the fundamentall Articles of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all errors overthrowing the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or tending to overthrow the ſame, ſhould be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That in matters ceremoniall and of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, there ſhould be a mutuall tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That betwixt the parties united, ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and uprightneſs ſhould be maintained, leſt ancient Errours might he upheld under doubtfull ſpeeches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That when peace is made, none ſhould be ſuffered to maintain, excuſe, or ſpread any more the Errors once condemned</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That ambitious and needleſs Diſputes and brablings ſhould be inhibited on all ſides</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204906:8"/>7. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1637</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That former reproaches and injuries ſhould be put to oblivion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>That the Church-Government ſhould be ſettled according to Apoſtolical Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe demands the reſt agreed unto, neither was any thing of moment added thereunto by any. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned back again into <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Lords Regents of that which was paſt, thoughts were entertained about the firſt and the laſt of theſe Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the chief of all the reſt; namely, concerning Fundamentall Articles of Faith, and the eſtabliſhment of Eccleſiaſticall Government. Touching the firſt, namely, how to limitate the number of Fundamentals, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the ſame from not-Fundamentals, Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part a brief Diſcourſe unto thoſe of <hi>Ubſall,</hi> to which they made no reply, as being loth to go too faſt, before they ſhould have the conſent of their Brethren, yet ſilently they aſſented thereunto. Concerning the ſecond, becauſe they then were in deliberation to ſettle their Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Canons, which they were about to make. Therefore both the Dean of the Faculty of Divinity at <hi>Ubſall,</hi> the Queens Tutor at <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and the Lord Chancellor, conferred ſeveral times with Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> about that matter, to know the Conſtitutions of the chief Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches; wherein he laboured to give them ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; and imparted unto them alſo the printed judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Engliſh Prelates, Doctor <hi>Morton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Hall,</hi> which beſides ſome other publick Treatiſes of the ſame nature, were communicated unto them. But the Lord Chancellor being deſirous to confer more particularly, and at leiſure, with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> about all matters belonging to the further advancing of the work of pacification, took him along in his company and Coach towards <hi>Ubſall,</hi> in a Circuit which he made thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therward from <hi>Stockholm,</hi> thorow <hi>Strengneſe,</hi> and <hi>Weſteroſe.</hi> In this progreſs the Biſhops of <hi>Strengneſe</hi> and <hi>Weſteroſe</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204906:9"/>were dealt withall the ſecond time.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
               </note> They ſetled good reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and laid grounds for conſtant future Treaties; ſo far, that they had thoughts of ſending ſome body into <hi>England;</hi> nevertheleſs, before matters could be brought to full maturity, ſome of the <hi>German Lutherans</hi> hearing large reports of Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s proceeding in <hi>Sweden,</hi> and being moved with jealouſie that the <hi>Swedes</hi> would come to ſome publick Treaties, and therein to a Concluſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, did expoſtulate the matter, and by Letters en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to diſſwade them from all further entertaining of his motions, by which means their ſpirits were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and their reſolutions ſo clogged, that from that time forward, they went heavily to work; yet Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> hoping to overcome all ſuch letts, did not leave the work, but laboured ſo much the more to engage them to it, by ſhewing ways free from all exception, whereby the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which they did ſtick at, might be compoſed. This he did firſt at <hi>Ubſall,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Stockholm,</hi> in a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the chief Clergie, which was commanded to deal with him; wherein he gave them ſatisfaction to all their demands, in a whole days conference inſtituted to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo that they ſeemed to acquieſſe. And becauſe they had laid this as a main ground, That if a Fundamentall agreement could be found in the Doctrine of the Lords Supper, they would not much ſtand to debate other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Therefore not long after their conference, he offered to the Archbiſhop and Profeſſors of <hi>Ubſall,</hi> a learned and patheticall Declaration, which from the Univerſity of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdein,</hi> and Miniſtry of <hi>Edinburg,</hi> was ſent unto him, to ſhew the fundamentall agreement of Proteſtants in that point. At this Declaration ſome ſmall exceptions were taken, in reſpect of certain forms of ſpeeches contained therein; which Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having fully explained, and thereby reſolved their doubts, thoſe of <hi>Ubſall</hi> did reſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; but ſome others there were, who having ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves profeſſedly againſt the work, would by no means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any content. For the more humbly and diſcreetly it was offered unto them, the more they ſought to avoid it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204906:9"/>and laboured by all means to cry down and diſcredit the very purpoſe of agreement, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1638</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
               </note> leſt the good liking which the Lords Regents did ſhew thereunto, might take ſome reall effect, and work upon the ſpirits of the common Clergie a good impreſſion to give way unto it. This their perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being fully apparent, moved Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> to deal in ſome kinde more ſtrictly with them, than otherwiſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination would have ſuffered him to do; yet at laſt, to avoid occaſions of ſtrife, he reſolved to depart from thence, and let the buſineſs lie a while aſleep; but leſt ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable men might falſly traduce all his proceedings in his abſence, as then already in his preſence they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to do, by miſ-informing others of his words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and miſ-interpreting ſuſpiciouſly his aim, he cauſed to print (before he went away from thence) a Summary and true Narrative of all his chief actions, and Propoſals which he offered to the Clergie of that Kingdom met in a Convocation. And afterward, to the end they ſhould have no juſt cauſe of falſe ſurmiſes, or pretext to traduce his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, he made a ſolemn Vow to binde himſelf to law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full purpoſes, and unblameable ways of proceeding, which he put to paper and preſented to the Lord Chancellor, to be imparted unto the chief of that Clergie. Theſe preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being uſed, when he was reſolved to be gone, the Lords Regents were pleaſed in the Queens Name to give him a Declaration and dimiſſory Letter, whereby his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Sweden</hi> were approved, bearing witneſs that Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> being come into <hi>Sweden</hi> to diſpoſe the minds of their Clergie unto the work of Peace Eccleſiaſticall, according to the grounds laid by the States of the Empire at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Anno</hi> 1634. he had dealt by permiſſion and command of her Majeſty, with the chief Divines of that Kingdom; and although ſome difficulties were riſen, as in weighty matters is uſual, yet that he had not omitted any thing which could ſerve for the taking away of the ſame. Thus he went from <hi>Stockholm, Anno</hi> 1638. and came to <hi>Lubeck,</hi> there he had ſpeech with Dr. <hi>Hunnius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Lubeck.</hi>
               </note> one of the chief Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of thoſe quarters. Him he prepared to entertain the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204906:10"/>motion of Peace,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durye</hi>'s being at <hi>Lubick</hi> and <hi>Hamburg.</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1639</label> which afterward ſhould be made unto him. From <hi>Lubeck</hi> he ſet forward towards <hi>Hamburg</hi> to meet Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> who there was reſiding as Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour Extraordinary from his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and Princes of <hi>Germany.</hi> To him he gave attendance all the while he ſtaid in thoſe parts, not leaving his former purpoſe, but rather uſing the advantage of his Lordſhips favourable countenance.</p>
            <p>In this new period of the Negotiation, he went ſlowly to work, firſt becauſe he looked towards the <hi>Swedes,</hi> how they would behave themſelves after his departure; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe he waited for ſome overture to begin, and make ſome Propoſals at the publick Treaties of Peace in <hi>Germany,</hi> which then was thought upon by reaſon of the Emperours Ambaſſadour, who was come to thoſe parts, and the Mediators which did offer themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that Negotiation. But when thoſe Treaties were not likely to proceed,<note place="margin">At <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> he went to <hi>Bremen,</hi> that he might acquaint the Divines of that place with his former procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and gain in time to come their aſſiſtance by way of counſel. Theſe were very cordial in the buſineſs, and entertaining him with all kindneſs and liberality (which no <hi>Germans</hi> before them had done) ſuch encouragements and declarations were given, as he could deſire, both from the Clergie, and Magiſtrate of that City. Then he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded towards the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad.</hi>
               </note> who was at <hi>Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad;</hi> there with the good liking and countenance of my Lord Ambaſſadour, he acquainted the Lord Chancellor <hi>Raventclow</hi> with his deſire to deal with the Clergie of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> if his Majeſty would give him leave ſo to do. His Majeſty gave way to his demands, and was pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend certain Writings (which his Chancellor recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>) unto the conſideration of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Univerſity of <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe gave their judgment and advice concerning his Negotiation, tending to ſhew their approbation of the purpoſe, their particular counſel, and propoſals in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, and their willingneſs to treat further about it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204906:10"/>with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad.</hi>
               </note> if his Majeſty would give permiſſion thereunto.</p>
            <p>The King cauſed their judgment to be delivered to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Dury;</hi> who thereupon did accept of the offer of their Treaty, and gave them a large Anſwer to all their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, containing divers overtures towards a conſtant progreſs in a Theological way of Treaty. Unto this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by His Majeſties command, they gave a further De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of their judgment; whereunto Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving replied, and ſhewed his Majeſty a brief and ready way to come to the purpoſe, the King was pleaſed to write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Lord Ambaſſadour, to let him know that he thought it fit Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſhould be more particularly authorized from <hi>England,</hi> before the matter could proceed betwixt him and his Divines to any iſſue. Whiles theſe matters were thus in agitation, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> dealt alſo with the Magiſtrates and Miniſtry of <hi>Hamburg</hi> and <hi>Lubeck,</hi> and with the Illuſtrious Archbiſhop of <hi>Bremen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> who gave him a reference to ſome chief Divines, who entertained his motions with very good liking, and gave him an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſame.<note place="margin">at <hi>Stade.</hi>
               </note> In like manner he made Propoſals to thoſe of <hi>Stade,</hi> who took the ſame into mature conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promiſed to concur with others in anſwering. At laſt he went to thoſe of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and <hi>Luneburg,</hi> where,<note place="margin">at <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyck.</hi>
               </note> with the ſingular favour of thoſe Princes, and by the moſt pious and peaceable inclinations of their Counſellors and chief Divines, towards the work of Reconcilement, a ground was laid for a very effectual progreſs. For they have made the work their own, undertaking to diſpoſe the reſt of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches and Univerſities unto a real concurrence in it, that afterwards they may proceed with our Churches joyntly, to a full concluſion.</p>
            <p>Duke <hi>Augustus</hi> of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> was the firſt to whom Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> made his addreſs: this learned and wiſe Prince was pleaſed, in favour of the Work, not only to convocate his chief Divines, and appoint them, with ſome of his Counſellors of State, to confer Collegially a whole day with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> but alſo to ſettle a reſolution,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204906:11"/>which his Divines ſubſcribed,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Hildeſheim.</hi>
               </note> obliging themſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to joyn in all the waies of agreement, whereof they had conferred together: and moreover, to recommend the matter to his Couſin Duke <hi>George,</hi> by a large and moſt effectual Letter.</p>
            <p>With this addreſs he came to Duke <hi>George,</hi> reſiding at <hi>Hildeſheim,</hi> where he had no leſs, but rather more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable entertainment then he had gotten at <hi>Brunſwick.</hi> For by an Act of Councell the chief Divines, who then were in place, were appointed to viſit and entertain him, till others that were ſent for ſhould come: And when the chief of them were come, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> was lodged and entertained with them in one houſe at the Princes charge, for the ſpace of fourteen days, that they together might ripen matters, and bring their thoughts to a head. Which being done, a Committee of ſome Counſellors of State was appointed to give them publick audience in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Name, to hear them confer upon the matter of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to conſider their Counſels and joynt reſolutions, and to make relation thereof unto the Prince, that by his Authority and Countenance, ſuch aſſiſtance might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Work in due time, as ſhould be thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: All which being done, firſt the Divines gave to Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> a Theological Declaration, wherein they te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified their agreement to all his Propoſals, and then their more particular reſolutions concerning the manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding which they would follow in the future advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Work on their part, were alſo imparted unto him. The ſubſtance whereof was this:</p>
            <p>That Doctor <hi>Calixtus</hi> chief Profeſſor of the Univerſity of <hi>Helmeſtat,</hi> ſhould by order of the Prince put forth ſome Treaties, wherein the heads of matters in diſpute amongſt Proteſtants ſhould be handled hiſtorically out of Antiquity, to ſhew what the Church of all ages hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved thereof; and how, notwithſtanding ſome difference of opinion thereabout among the ancient Fathers, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love was alwaies maintained. Theſe Treaties ſhould be thus improved: Firſt, they ſhould be ſent unto the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:204906:11"/>Univerſities of <hi>Wittenburg, Leipzigh, Iena, Marpurg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being in <hi>Hildeſheim.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Roſtock,</hi> and alſo to thoſe of <hi>Brandenburg, Heſſen</hi> and <hi>Bremen,</hi> to move them to declare their judgments therein for mutuall agreement. Then, at ſome fit occaſion ſome body ſhould go to <hi>Leipzigh</hi> and <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and deal with the <hi>Saxon</hi> Electoral Profeſſors by word of mouth, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe them to a full reſolution in this buſineſs. To which effect alſo the Prince ſhould move the two Dukes of <hi>Saxon Weymer,</hi> Duke <hi>William,</hi> and Duke <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> who have long wiſhed for this Reconciliation, to cauſe their Univerſity of <hi>Iena</hi> to co-operate therein; And in proceſs of time, when the buſineſs ſhould be brought by this way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to ſome conſiderable ripeneſs, then it ſhould be moved, that from <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and elſewhere ſome body might be joyned to Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> and alſo from <hi>Germany</hi> ſome body ſhould go into <hi>England,</hi> and other parts, to ſpeak with the chief Divines of thoſe Churches, that when there ſhould be good hopes of bringing the matter to paſs, the Soveraign Princes and States of all ſides ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to agree upon a meeting, to make ſome concluſion in the matter: for the good ſucceſs whereof, publick prayers ſhould be made with common conſent in all the Churches.</p>
            <p>Theſe reſolutions being taken, when the Prince himſelf had ſpoken to Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> and given him aſſurance of his willingneſſe to ſet forward this purpoſe, he did diſmiſſe him with a recommendatory Letter unto his brother, Duke <hi>Frederick,</hi> reſiding at <hi>Zelle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zelle.</note> who in like manner received Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> very kindly, and moved his Divines to confer with him. In this conference, when they had received ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to ſome doubts which were propoſed, they gave conſent unto all which was concluded at <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and <hi>Hildeſheim.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luneburg.</note> From <hi>Zelle</hi> he went to the free <hi>City of Lune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> where he acquainted the Miniſtry of the place with his propoſalls made unto other Churches, that they might alſo take the ſame into their conſideration, and in due time with conſent of their Protector, D<hi rend="sup">k</hi>. <hi>Frederick,</hi> reſolv what to do therein.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:204906:12"/>
            <p>Thus the Circuit of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and <hi>Luneburg</hi> being fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Gluckſtat.</hi>
               </note> he returned to <hi>Hamburgh</hi> in <hi>February,</hi> An. 1640. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1640</label> from whence without delay he went towards my Lord Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> who was at <hi>Gluckſtad,</hi> with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to giue him account of all the paſſages of his proceedings. There he alſo dealt further with the Lord Chauncellor, <hi>Detloff Raventlow,</hi> and the King himſelf was pleaſed, upon my Lord Ambaſſador his recommendation, to give him acceſſe to kiſſe his hand, and in preſence of his Son, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bremen,</hi> to ſpeak with him about the ſetting forward of his purpoſe. In which diſcourſe, his Majeſty ſhewed a good liking to his proceedings, and gave way that if he thought fit, he ſhould make new propoſalls, touching means of Reconcilement, unto his Divines, that they might have further occaſion to entertain theſe thoughts as well as others. Hereupon Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part unto the forenamed Lord Chancellor, a paper, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining certain heads, fit to be Theolagically conſulted upon by them, that their reſolutions touching the ſame, might in due time be framed, and alſo made publick, if they themſelvs thought it expedient. Thus the Treaties at <hi>Denmark</hi> being again ſet on foot, hee returned from <hi>Gluck ſtad</hi> with my Lord Ambaſſador towards <hi>Hamburg,</hi> and gave by letters, information into <hi>England,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all matters of moment, which paſſed in his work. Then alſo ſom writingspreſented formerly unto the Divines of <hi>Denmark,</hi> were made publick, that many who deſired to know the paſſages of that negotiation, might have ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction therein. Not long after, my Lord Ambaſſador was recalled from <hi>Germeny</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> about which time the private diſputes amongſt thoſe of <hi>Bremen</hi> were come to ſome height: for thoſe that were moſt inclinable to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuffering wrong, had ſought: Maſter <hi>Dury's</hi> advice, and deſired his help to compoſe their doubtfull queſtions. Therefore he ſent to ſome of the Prelates of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome of the Profeſſors of Divinity, in both Univerſities, certain writings, which the chief Divines of <hi>Bremen</hi> ſubmitted unto their judgments,<note place="margin">at <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> containing the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204906:12"/>true ſtate of their difference, <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at</note> which reflected much upon the main controverſie debated betwixt the reformed, and the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divines; therefore the deciſion thereof, was thought to be a ſingular preparative for the common and more publick Unity of all Proteſtants. To theſe writings the Biſhops of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and of <hi>Exceter</hi> gave their anſwers, and the reſt to whom they were ſent, promiſed to do the like; In the mean time Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ripened, ſomwhat matters towards the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and endeavoured to ſmooth the knottineſſe of the Clergy of <hi>Hamburg</hi> and <hi>Lubeck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For finding ſome warping of their intentions,<note place="margin">At <hi>Lubeck.</hi>
               </note> which he perceived would bend another way then was expedient; hee dealt firſt with Doctor <hi>Hunnius</hi> a leading man at <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> and then with the Senior Preacher of <hi>Hamburg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">at <hi>Hamburg</hi>
               </note> that when theſe two ſhould bee ſet in a right way, the leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing and more clamarous Clergy might be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perſwaded, and wrought to admit the thoughts of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. As for Doctor <hi>Calixtus,</hi> although ſome men of ſtrife, and evill willers to him, did undertake to diſturb him in theſe peaceable thoughts, yet being ſtrongly countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Superiors, hee began to perform his promiſe, and gave Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> full aſſurance of his conſtancy, and of the concurrence of many others towards the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſame Councells. And becauſe the oppoſition made againſt Doctor <hi>Calixtus,</hi> by his Brethren, was like unto that which the chief Profeſſors of <hi>Bremen</hi> ſuffered by their Brethren, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> conceived that the ſimilitude of their caſes, might be a motive to induce them to mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all correſpondency, in the work of reconcilement. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having gotten the Originall Writings which Biſhop <hi>Davenant,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> ſent to thoſe of <hi>Bremen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> hee went thither, to deliver the ſame, and conferre with them about the matter, whereunto hee found them exceeding well inclined. In the way going thither, hee dealt with one <hi>Statius Buſcherus,</hi> Doctor <hi>Calixtus</hi> his chief oppoſer, endeavouring to mollifie and withdraw him from ſome prepoſterous courſes: and coming back again, hee ſtayed a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204906:13"/>whole day at <hi>Bremenvorde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Bremer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorde.</hi>
               </note> the Reſidence of the Illuſtrious Archbiſhop of <hi>Bremen,</hi> with whom he had twice occaſion of large conference, tending to give him ſatisfaction (which hee alſo received) concerning ſome doubts, which hee had conceived of the Work. From thence paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through <hi>Stade,</hi>
               <note place="margin">at <hi>Stade.</hi>
               </note> and having inſinuated unto the chief Preacher of that place M. <hi>Haveman</hi> ſome writings tending to Pacification,<note place="margin">at <hi>Buxte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bude.</hi>
               </note> hee arrived at <hi>Buxtethude</hi> where hee met with Maſter <hi>Scholvinus</hi> the Paſtor of the place, a learned and moderate <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divine, whom hee confirmed in a courſe of conference, and correſpondency, begun with Doctor <hi>Bergius</hi> at <hi>Bremen,</hi> towards the ripening of matters belonging to Pacification.</p>
            <p>Then being come back to <hi>Hamburg</hi> hee made himſelf ready to return for <hi>England:</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </note> And to this effect took his leave of the Magiſtrate, and Miniſtry of that place; ſome of the Magiſtrate were very earneſt with him to perſevere in the proſecuting of his work, and the Miniſtry gave him their anſwer in writ, ſhewing that they were willing to proceed; firſt, by way of private correſpondency in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and then by way of publick meeting, when things ſhould be repined. Before he went from <hi>Hamburg</hi> he ſent by Sea to the chief Prelates, who in <hi>England</hi> had aſſiſted him, a Treatiſe, which Doctor <hi>Calixtus</hi> of <hi>Helmiſtat,</hi> had written in behalf of the work, that they might declare their judgment unto him concerning the ſame. Then he paſſed again through <hi>Buxtehude,</hi> and <hi>Stade,</hi> where hee confirmed Maſter <hi>Haveman</hi> and <hi>Scholvinus,</hi> in their reſolutions to moderation, and dealt again with <hi>Statius Buſcherus,</hi> to take off the edge of his ſpirit againſt Doctor <hi>Calixtus.</hi> At <hi>Bremen</hi> hee ſtayed fourteen days,<note place="margin">at <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> to print an Information directed to all the Reformed Churches, concerning the Councells of peace, whereunto the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſide did give way, that if the ſame ſhould finde on the reformed ſide in like manner approbation, the buſineſſe might bee in due time ſet forward by publick authority.<note place="margin">at <hi>Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> at <hi>Embden.</hi>
               </note> From <hi>Bremen</hi> hee went to <hi>Oldenburg,</hi> where he dealt with the Superintendent of that place, and by his means preſented to the Earl
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204906:13"/>of <hi>Oldenbueg</hi> that which was fit to give him informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his work. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1641</label> From thence hee came to <hi>Embden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Groningen.</hi>
               </note> where hee ſtayed certain days, to inſinuate the printed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation unto the Divines, both of the City,<note place="margin">at <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi>
               </note> and of the County. At <hi>Groningen</hi> hee did the like: from whence coming to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </note> hee conferred with the chief Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of his acquaintance there, and ſent to all the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries (which they call <hi>Claſſes</hi>) of <hi>North-Holland,</hi> and neighbouring parts, ſo many copies of the printed information, with adjoined letters, as were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to bee imparted unto them. From the <hi>Hague</hi> hee did the like unto all the <hi>Presbyters of South-Holland and Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of the neighbouring places, as alſo to the <hi>Synods</hi> which were to bee held in every Province. Thus having given ſatisfaction to the chief of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed means to ſend information from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> into <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetia,</hi> and from the <hi>Hague</hi> into <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> hee came to <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and took Shipping for <hi>Eengland:</hi> Where being ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrived, hee made his application to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, and to all that were in power and place to move them to countenance and aſſiſt his deſigne, but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion between the King and Parlament increaſing daily; his motions though not unſeaſonable, yet were not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually entertained by any either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> becauſe ſeverall applications being made to the Churches, and to the men of eminency in both Nations, all the year 1641. hee found all to bee in vain, be cauſe every one was intent upon his particular occaſions,<note place="margin">the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </note> and all minding one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Domeſtick grievances; the common intereſt of Proteſtants could not bee laid to heart: therefore when hee ſaw that nothing could bee effected or intended, ſo long as the differences were like to grow greater; hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of a Call, which was given him to the Court of the Princeſſe Royall at the <hi>Hague,</hi> to attend the Service of that family in the education of that Princeſſe. Hee was in that imploiment in the years 1642, 1643. till he received a Summons from the Parlament, whereby hee was called unto the Aſſembly of Divines; and becauſe tht Prince of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204906:14"/>
               <hi>Orange</hi> would not give him conſent to go thither,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durye</hi>'s being <hi>in England</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1645. till 1654.</label> nor could hee find any comfort in his imploiment at Court, hee reſigned his charge at that place, and accepted of the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l which the Marchant-adventurers at <hi>Roterdam</hi> gave him, to bee the Miniſter of their Company: there hee was in the year 1644. and the firſt Summons whereby hee was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto the Aſſembly of Divines, beeing ſtill inſiſted upon; he went from <hi>Rotterdam</hi> in the year 1645. and cam to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where in the ſervice of the Churches, for the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Domeſtick differences, he imploied himſelf between all emergent parties, till the year 1654. So the work of his publick Negotiation for the Unity of Proteſtants was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended for the ſpace of almoſt thirteen years; wherein he entertained onely a correſpondency by letters with ſome of the Divines of his acquaintance beyond the Seas, to keep the thoughts of ſo good a work a foot amongſt them, ſo far as the times could permit.</p>
            <p>Then the Peace being happily concluded between <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and the United Provinces, on the fifth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1654. Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having gotten his Highneſſe the Lord Protectors approbation and countenance, for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his deſign of Pacification amongſt Proteſtants, and having obtained the aſſiſtance of the two Univerſities, and of the chief Miniſters in and about <hi>London,</hi> to concurre with him in his endeavours,<note place="margin">In the <hi>Low Countreys</hi> In <hi>high Germany.</hi> in <hi>Switzer Land at Zurich.</hi>
               </note> he went from <hi>London</hi> on the foreſaid day of <hi>April;</hi> and through the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and a part of <hi>High Germany,</hi> hee came to <hi>Zurich</hi> in <hi>Switzerland</hi> on the eighteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> where having delivered his <hi>Highneſſes</hi> letter inſcribed to the Proteſtant Cantons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending his deſigne unto them; thoſe of <hi>Zurich</hi> at his deſire appointed three profeſſors of Divinity and three of the chief Miniſters to treat with him; till they ſhould call a meeting of deputies from all the other Reformed Cantons to hear his propoſalls, that a generall reſolution might bee taken to carry on his work. This meeting was held at <hi>Araw,</hi> in the Canton of <hi>Berne,</hi> on the thirteenth of <hi>June;</hi> where Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having propoſed the ſcope of his Negotiation, and the main grounds upon which it was to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204906:14"/>be agitated,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Zurich.</hi>
               </note> and communicated ſome Documents to bee conſidered of by all the Cantons; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1654</label> the deputies returned home, and made report of that which had been propoſed and imparted unto them; and on the twenty ſeventh day of the following Moneth, the Generall Reſolution of the Cantons was delivered in writing to him by the Senate of <hi>Zurich;</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July 27"/> which was to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Cantons rejoiced much to find his Highneſſes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable affection expreſſed unto them; and acknowledged it a great honour, that hee had acquainted them before others, with his purpoſe to advance the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Proteſtants in Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to</hi> Maſter Dury's <hi>propoſall and ſcope, they gave their full aſſent as to a work moſt commendable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they would not onely commend it to all their Churches and Academies, but would concurre to further it with their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to find the effect of this their imclination, they, invited him to viſit their chief Cities and Academies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Intreating him withall to teſtifie unto his Highneſs, their reciprocall love and affection; and that his recommendatory letters have with them a great weight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had even made an end of his Theologicall Treatiſe with the Divines of <hi>Zurich:</hi>
               <note place="margin">at <hi>Zurich.</hi>
               </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, their agreement concerning the meanes and manner of proceeding, by which the ſcope of his deſigne might bee obtained was ſet down. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Augu. 5"/> Therefore upon the declaration of the Cantons, whereby hee was invited to viſit their chief Cities and Churches, hee went from <hi>Zurich</hi> to <hi>Berne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Berne.</hi>
               </note> Where hee arrived the fifth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and having ſaluted the chief Magiſtrate, and treated with the Divines whom they appointed to hear his propoſalls, hee came to a full concluſion with them; wherein they agreed to all that had been reſolved upon at <hi>Zurich;</hi> and when they had given him at a full meeting of the Miniſtry and of the profeſſors;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204906:15"/>their declaration in writing,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Baſel.</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1654. in Sept.</label> whereby the ſame was atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, hee went from thence and came to <hi>Baſel</hi> the firſt <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Baſel</hi> he proceeded in the ſame way, for having ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the chief Magiſtrate, and gotten ſix Deputies appointed to treat with him: Some of the Miniſters and ſome of the Profeſſors of that Univerſitie; hee dealt with them to the ſame effect as he had done with thoſe of <hi>Zurich</hi> and <hi>Berne,</hi> onely they varied a little in their declaration concerning the way of proceeding; adding ſome advices and limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the work which the others had not expreſſed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had not been unmindfull of them; and after a publick entertainment which the Magiſtrate made for Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> and all the Miniſters and Profeſſors, he went to <hi>Schaffhuſen,</hi> where being com the 20 of <hi>October,</hi> by the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Sena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the whole Miniſtry was convocated with the profeſſors of the School,<note place="margin">Schaffhu. ſen.</note> and ſom of the Senators being preſent, he had audience on the twenty fifth, wherein rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his progreſſe, he communicated unto them the matters tranſacted at <hi>Zurich, Berne</hi> and <hi>Baſell,</hi> deſiring them to impart unto him, their judgment concerning the ſame; which they did on the twelfth of <hi>November</hi> following by a written Declaration, approving Maſter <hi>Durys</hi> deſigne and concurring with the reſt to further it: Theſe four chief Cantons beeing ſeverally prepared thus to concur; it was moved by thoſe of <hi>Schaffhuſen,</hi> that the Canton of <hi>Zurich,</hi> ſhould according to former Cuſtoms begin to think of a common Declaration which might be given to Maſter <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in the name of all;<note place="margin">Zurich.</note> this they reſolved to do as ſoon as Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſhould have made an end of going through the reſt of the Churches; therefore beeing returned to <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich;</hi> by their advice hee went to S. <hi>Gall,</hi> thither alſo the Deputies of the Cantons of <hi>Appenzall</hi> (beeing forewarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the time of Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s coming) were ſent;<note place="margin">S. <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </note> that at that time hee might meet with the Miniſters of both pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a Synodical way;<note place="margin">Appenzel.</note> which was done in the preſence of ſome of the Magiſtrates of S. <hi>Gall,</hi> on the twenty eight of <hi>November.</hi> And having given them at large an informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204906:15"/>on of all that was formerly done in his work,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being neer the border of the <hi>Griſons.</hi>
               </note> and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red afterward with ſome of the chief, concerning particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar matters; hee went towards the borders of the <hi>Griſons</hi> (whiles they ſhould prepare the Declaration which they would reſolve to give him) that hee might in a place of ſafety; confer with ſome, who from the Churches of the <hi>Griſons</hi> were to give him a meeting without being obſerved. To that place he went in <hi>December,</hi> and there having ſpent one whole day, and a part of another, in conference with thoſe that came thither to him; hee returned to S. <hi>Gall;</hi> received their approbatorie Declaration, and went back to <hi>Zurich</hi> to adviſe with them what courſe ſhould be taken to deal with their other confederates:<note place="margin">Zurich.</note> theſe deliberations being brought to ſome concluſion, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went from <hi>Zurich</hi> towards <hi>Berne,</hi> where on the twenty third hee arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and with their advice and by their addreſſe to the places of ſafety within their Dominion, hee ſet forward and dealt firſt with the Miniſters of <hi>Biel,</hi> then with thoſe of <hi>Neuſtat,</hi> thirdly with thoſe of <hi>Neuſchatel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Berne</note> and in the way towards <hi>Lauſanna</hi> with the chief preacher of every conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable town, till on the twelfth of <hi>January,</hi> 1655. he came to <hi>Lauſanna;</hi> where as in other places, by the Magiſtrat's Direction hee conferred with the Miniſters and Profeſſors of that Church and Academie,<note place="margin">Lauſanua.</note> and having furniſhed them with ſufficient information concerning his proceedings, hee left them preparing the Declaration which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give him at his return from <hi>Geneva;</hi> for thither hee was bent; and was to return back again the ſame way.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Geneva</hi> hee arrived on the twentieth, and ſtayed there ten days; hee had a Letter from his Highneſs the Lord Protector to the Magiſtrate of that place, which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, the whole Miniſtry of the City and Territorie, with the Profeſſors of the Academy; came together and received the information, which was at large delivered unto them, by Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> concerning his work. This being done on the twenty third, they appointed Deputies who treated with him day by day, afterward concerning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204906:16"/>the particulars which hee offered unto their conſideration;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1655</label> whereof the chief matter was concerning the <hi>Harmony</hi> of Confeſſions to bee put by them in another forme, then formerly it hath been in: Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> thought it not fit to make any long ſtay there, leſt being much obſerved, his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation at the Court of <hi>France</hi> (whence many ſpies are upon <hi>Geneva</hi>) might become ſuſpected, and ſo prejudiciall unto their good correſpondency there, for this cauſe hee made haſt to bee gone, not ſtaying for their anſwer in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but referring them to ſend it after him towards <hi>Berne</hi> (whither hee was purpoſed to returne) hee came on the firſt of <hi>February</hi> to <hi>Lauſanna,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Feb."/> where having received the judgment of that Church and Academy,<note place="margin">Berne.</note> hee ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and came on the ſeventh to <hi>Berne.</hi> There hee ſtayed to print ſome thing which was to bee ſent to <hi>Geneva,</hi> that it might bee by them diſperſed amongſt the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> to cure them of ſome prejudices which were taken up againſt his work by ſome in that Kingdom, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their anſwers which they promiſed to ſend unto him:<note place="margin">Araw.</note> which things being being performed; hee went to <hi>Araw,</hi> where hee found the Deputies of all the Proteſtant Cantons at a meeting, to whom hee gave an account of the ſucceſs of his Negociation, thanked them for their aſſiſtance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to move their Churches to give him their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Declaration to bee made uſe of, in the name of all, to adde a Declaration in their own name thereunto, as a State, and to write to the German Princes of the reformed Religion, to preinformthem of this Negotiation, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themto a Concurrance in the work at Mr. <hi>Dury's</hi> arival amongſt them. To theſe propoſals they gave their aſſent; and Mr.<note place="margin">Zurich.</note> 
               <hi>Dury</hi> went forward to <hi>Zurich,</hi> where on the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeventh of <hi>February</hi> hee arrived; and haviving given them an account of his proceedings in all the quarters where he had been, ſince the time hee had been abſent from them; he moved them (by the means of a Divine who came from <hi>Berne</hi> with him for that end) to ſettle a neerer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency between themſelves and thoſe of <hi>Berne,</hi> in the proſecution of this work.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:204906:16"/>
            <p>At <hi>Zurich</hi> hee ſtayed all <hi>March, and April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Baſel.</hi>
               </note> and a part of <hi>May</hi> following, to write letters to all parts, to expect the promiſed Declarations of the Church and State; to print ſome preliminary informations to bee ſent before hand into <hi>Germany;</hi> to ſettle the courſe of a Theologicall Correſpondency; and to receive the anſwer of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Cantons to his Highneſs Letter; which things bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done he went to <hi>Baſel</hi> and came thither on the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Baſel,</hi> having informed the Divines of all that was paſt, and propoſed unto them the courſe of correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy agreed upon by the other Cantons, and received a letter from the Magiſtrate of the place to his Highneſs the Lord Protector; in anſwer to that which hee had formerly brought unto them from him: and when hee alſo had treated with the Prince Elector Palatins Agent <hi>Charles Mieg</hi> reſiding at <hi>Baſel,</hi> how to correſpond at a diſtance in the Negotiation with his Prince; becauſe for ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of State, the Prince was not willing to have Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> come to <hi>Heidelberg</hi> to him: hee took his journey through the Dukedom of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> towards <hi>Hanaw;</hi> in the way he ſtayed one day at <hi>Stutgard,</hi> which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of the Prince;<note place="margin">Stutgard.</note> there although the Duke was in great heavineſſe by reaſon of the ſickneſſe of his Lady (who dyed ſoon after), yet having underſtood that Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> was in the town; hee cauſed ſome of his Counſell to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him, to confer with him concerning his buſineſſe, that he might know the true intent thereof, and to ſettle a way of correſpondency in time to come about it, as one who deſired to co-operate towards the furthering of it.</p>
            <p>On the fourteenth of <hi>June</hi> hee came to <hi>Hanaw</hi> (one of the chief towns of the <hi>Wetteraw</hi>), <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="June."/> 
               <note place="margin">Hanaw.</note> there hee ſtayed to deal with the Miniſtry of the place; and to print ſuch papers as were neceſſary to bee ſent abroad, to all the reformed Churches of <hi>Germany,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July"/> and to their Princes for information. At this time there was a meeting of the Deputies of the States of the Empire at <hi>Franck fort;</hi>
               <note place="margin">at <hi>Bremen.</hi>
               </note> this gave Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204906:17"/>opportunity to meet with the Ambaſſadors of the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med party;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Wetteraw.</hi> &amp; <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
               </note> and to make uſe of their addreſſes, in ſending the papers of Information to their Princes and Churches. And whiles he ſtayed at <hi>Hanaw</hi> he acquainted the Prince Elector Palatine with all his proceedings, and by the means of Doctor <hi>Hottinger,</hi> who was appointed his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent, hee ſatisfied all his ſcruples. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Auguſt."/> In this kind of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> continued till the fifth of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> and becauſe before that time hee had received ſome anſwers from moſt of the Churches of the <hi>Wetteraw,</hi> to which hee had written; and the Declaration of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the City and County of <hi>Hanaw;</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Septem."/> hee then begun to make a progreſs to viſit the particular Churches of that circle, that he might engage them diſtinctly to co-operate in his work. Thus he dealt effectually with the Earls of <hi>Yſenburg</hi> and <hi>Budingen</hi> and their Divines; at <hi>Offenback,</hi> at <hi>Wechtersback</hi> and at <hi>Birſtein.</hi> Then with the Earls of <hi>Solms,</hi> at <hi>Hoing,</hi> at <hi>Braunfells</hi> and <hi>Griffenſtein;</hi> and laſtly with the Divines and Counſellors of the Princes of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> at <hi>Herbone, Dillenberg, Sigen</hi> and <hi>Dietz;</hi> and with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor of the Earl of <hi>Witgenſtein</hi> (who is the Director of the Circle of the <hi>Wetteraw</hi>) himſelf being abſent with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> in <hi>Pruſſia:</hi> this circuit through the territories of the <hi>Wetteraw</hi> and of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> was ended before the end of <hi>September,</hi> then returning again to <hi>Hanaw</hi> to make ſome diſpatches; he ſtayed there till the eighteenth of <hi>October,</hi> from whence at that time he went into <hi>Heſſen,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Octob,"/> and arriving at <hi>Marpurg</hi> on the nineteenth he ſtayed there in conferences with the Profeſſors of Divinity of that Univerſity, Doctor <hi>Crocius</hi> and Doctor <hi>Curtius,</hi> eminent men of the reformed ſide,<note place="margin">Caſſel.</note> till the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Novem."/> then hee ſet forward and came to <hi>Caſſell</hi> on the third of that moneth; where having ſaluted the Prince, ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of the chief of the Miniſtry were appointed to hear his propoſalls, theſe having received the information which he imparted unto them, made a report thereof, unto the chief of the Princes privie Councell; who ſoon after conferred with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> to be cleered in ſome doubts,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204906:17"/>they had, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1655 Febru.</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at</note> concerning the propoſalls made unto the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: and they having received ſatisfaction therein; at Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s deſire, they aſſiſted him very affectionately,<note place="margin">Anhalt.</note> in furthering his deſignes by counſell, and by addreſſing and directing his Negotiation in the neighbouring Churches of <hi>Lowe Saxonte</hi> and <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and alſo towards the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and ſom other quarters with which Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did keep conſtant correſpondency; and in this courſe of acting with them, he continued till the latter end of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 1656. then he went from <hi>Caſſel</hi> towards <hi>Anhalt,</hi> and arrived at <hi>Deſſaw,</hi> where the Senior Prince of that Family reſides, to whom the direction of all common affairs doth belong: with his Chancellor Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance in former time, he had much freedom of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and a ready addreſſe unto the Prince, who favourably heard his propoſalls, and appointed his chief Divines and Counſellors to confer with him; who having made their report, and the matter being liked in Councell;<note place="margin">Anhalt.</note> a two-fold Declaration was drawn up, the one to be given Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> in the name of all the Princes; the other in the name of all the Superintendants; which were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him before he went out of the Principalitie of <hi>Anhalt:</hi> and after hee was gone from <hi>Deſſaw;</hi> for having taken his leave from the director, and ſaluted the Princes reſiding at <hi>Koeton,</hi> and at <hi>Berenburg,</hi> with each of whom he ſtayed but one day, he went to the Prince whoſe reſidence is at <hi>Pletzkow,</hi> whoſe ſingular courteſie and zeale towards the work obliged him to ſtay five days with him, during which time the Declarations aforeſaid were delivered unto Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> together with a letter or two of addreſſe unto ſome of the Counſellors of the Dukes of <hi>Weimor;</hi> for hee reſolved to returne through the Dukedome of <hi>Weimar</hi> towards <hi>Caſſell,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="March-"/> to the end that hee might by thoſe two Lutheran Princes ſeek ſome ouverture towards the reſt;<note place="margin">Weimar.</note> and by a cleer information gievn to them of his deſigne, prevent the falſe reports which might bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204906:18"/>raiſed,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durye's</hi> being at <hi>Weimar.</hi>
               </note> and remove the prejudices which were conceived by ſome concerning his work.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auon.</hi> 1656.</note> About the beginning of <hi>March</hi> hee was at the City of <hi>Weymar,</hi> and ſtayed two days for the Dukes arrivall who was not in the town; beeing then come home, hee gave Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> private audience, and having received the papers which were prepared to give him an inſight in his buſineſſes; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="March."/> hee diſcourſed thereof with Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> about the ſpace of two hours, hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his likeing to the work, and appointed one of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill to confer with Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> about ſome particulars; and when he went away, the Prince gave him a letter to his chief Counſellor; who is the Governour of the Dukedome of <hi>Iſennach;</hi> willing him to learn more fully of Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> the circumſtances of his way, that in due time they might judge what to do in it; from <hi>Weymar</hi> he went to <hi>Gotha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gotha.</note> where Duke <hi>Erneſtus</hi> lives, who is the younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him who lives at <hi>Weymar.</hi> With this Prince Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had a whole days conference, without any intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for hee ſent for him about eight in the morning, and continued till twelve; and then began again at two in the afternoon, and continued till ſix without any interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The next day hee ſent again unto Maſter. <hi>Dury</hi> by eight of the Clock, and appointed one of his Councill (becauſe other affairs did hinder himſelf, as hee told Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>) to confer with him, about the deſignes of advancing Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Learning, which hee did proſecute: and the ſame day again in the afternoon from about two, till evening, this Prince continued his diſcourſes with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> the Councellor whom in the morning hee had emploied being preſent; ſo that in effect two whole days were ſpent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in a ſerious propoſall and diſquirie, of the means and ways, by which true Chriſtian Unity and Goſpel Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of affections ſhould bee advanced amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; and the reſult of all was, that the Prince would contribute all that lay in his power to further the deſignes whereof they had conferred together; and that Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> was deſired in time to come to entertain a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204906:18"/>about the ſame with the Prince his Chancellor,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Iſennac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> or with the Gentleman then preſent, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656</label> who was Tutor to his Eldeſt Son. Thus thanking Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> for his coming to him, the Prince diſmiſſed him, and he went from thence to <hi>Iſennach.</hi> Where hee arrived on the ninth of <hi>March,</hi> there having delivered Duke <hi>William</hi> his Letter to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the place; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="March."/> hee ſtayed with him other two days, wherein hee had three times conference with him, for the ſpace of two or three hours at a time, and once at Supper, where others were preſent; they and hee entertained Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> in diſcourſes of his own buſineſſe, and of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick affairs of <hi>England,</hi> from ſix till almoſt twelve at night; the reſult of all was a full agreement to Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and a free engagement on his part to concurre therein, and to correſpond by Letters with him to that effect.</p>
            <p>Theſe buſineſſes beeing thus ſucceſsfully tranſacted in the Dukedom of <hi>Weymar,</hi> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went from <hi>Iſennach</hi> to <hi>Rotenburg</hi> on the twelfth,<note place="margin">Rotenburg</note> where <hi>Landgrave Herman</hi> the Uncle of <hi>Landgrave William of Caſſel</hi> reſides; to him (for he had given Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſom addreſſ both into <hi>Anhalt</hi> and to <hi>Weymar</hi>) he gave an account of his Negotiation in both places; and conſulted with him of a further progeſſe to bee made in the work.<note place="margin">Eſchwegen</note> From <hi>Rotenburg</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee went to <hi>Eſch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegen,</hi> where he dealt with the <hi>Swediſh Ambaſſador</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieur <hi>Horn;</hi> who reſided with the Kings Siſter in that place; at his Perſwaſion Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> wrote unto the King, to let him know the progreſſe of his work, both amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and alſo ſom of the <hi>Lutberan</hi> party. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aprill"/> 
               <note place="margin">Caſſel</note> From thence he returned on the ſeventeenth of <hi>March</hi> to <hi>Caſſel.</hi> Where having given the <hi>Landgrave</hi> an account of his proceedings; and acquainted the Provinciall Synod, which then was met at <hi>Caſſel</hi> therewith in like manner, hee ſtayed there till the eight of <hi>May</hi> to make a full end of his Negotiation in thoſe quarters, and to fit himſelf for his journey which he intended towards the Churches of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="May"/> which hee then took in hand and, arrived at the Academie of <hi>Rintelen</hi> in the County of <hi>Schaumburg</hi> on the eleventh. This Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204906:19"/>is wholly <hi>Lutheran,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Rintelen</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1664. May</label> but ſo moderate that Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> thought fit to make acquaintance with them to prepare them to co-operate with him in the work of Peace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Churches and Univerſities of their own ſide; with theſe <hi>Latheran</hi> Divines he ſpent nine days, to inform them of the way of his Negotiation, and of the progreſſe thereof, whereunto they having promiſed their concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, hee took the opportunity of viliting two Earls who were in the neighbourhood, <hi>viz.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Schaumburg,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Lippe;</hi> with whom and with ſome of their Preachers and Councellors hee conferred; to let them know the nature and chief circumſtances of his work, that they might countenance the furthering of it in their places; whith they promiſid to do.</p>
            <p>Then beeing gone from <hi>Rintelen</hi> on the 20 of <hi>May,</hi> hee came to <hi>Detmold</hi> in the County of <hi>Lippe,</hi> where having ſpent two days with the Superintendant of the place,<note place="margin">Detmeld</note> and the Earls Chancellor: to confirm them in the good incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which they had towards his buſineſſe; he ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and came to <hi>Tecklenburg,</hi> a ſeat of one of the Earls of <hi>Bentheim;</hi> there hee ſtayed eight days, in which time the Earl did convocate the chief of the Miniſtry of his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<note place="margin">Tecklen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</note> who having been preinformed before Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> came to them of his work they had prepared their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of it, which upon conference had with him they compleated and ſubſcribed; and the Earl with his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor having alſo conferred with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> and ſeen the Declarations of other Princes and States touching his work, he gave him his Declarations to further it in like manner; whereupon on the fifth of <hi>June</hi> being gone from thence hee came to <hi>Bentheim,</hi> where the two brethren Earls of that houſe young men couſins to him of <hi>Tecklen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> were then reſiding, who received Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> very courteouſly: and hee having in generall terms propoſed the intention of his coming to them, they appointed the Chancellor and two of the chief Miniſters of the place to confer with him, to underſtand the particular matters which were to be offered to the conſideration of their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204906:19"/>Churches, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. June</label> and of the profeſſors of the School at <hi>Steinfurt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Emdon</hi>
               </note> theſe having received the papers which were to bee Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to their Churches, the reſolution was taken to ſend them to their chief Miniſters abroad; and then to call them together that they might give their joint Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration concerning the bufineſſe. When this reſolution was made known to Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> he thought fit to redeem time, that whiles they ſhould be acquainting their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es with the particulars of his work; he ſhould go to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> to acquaint them with the ſame matters, and return back again thither by that time they ſhould have ripened their thoughts. Therefore he took his journey thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and on the thirteenth conferred with the Miniſtry of that place, and afterward with the chief of the Magiſtracy, and laſtly with the whole aſſociation of the Neighbour Miniſters; which conveniently was met on the ſecond day of the week, they all having promiſed their aſſiſtance and concurrence in the work; and taken a Reſolution to ſend unto him their written Declaration in due time, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="June"/> he left thoſe at <hi>Emden</hi> and came to <hi>Groningen,</hi> where hee confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Doctor <hi>Mareſius</hi> to renew old acquaintance,<note place="margin">Groningen</note> and to diſcourſe ſomewhat in a preparatorie way concerning his Negotiation; which being done he returned to <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theim</hi> on the twenty one day; there the Miniſters of the Counties of <hi>Benthem</hi> and <hi>Steinfurt,</hi> with the Divinity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the School met on the twenty ſixth and prepared their written Declaration,<note place="margin">Bentheim</note> which the day following they delivered unto Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> at their Aſſembly and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him of ſervall particulars wherein, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July"/> they deſired to have ſome more light then the papers imparted unto them could affoard; which being done to their ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;<note place="margin">Weſel</note> the Earls gave him afterward alſo jointly their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſigned and ſealed; whereupon the next day which was the firſt of <hi>July</hi> he ſet forward from thence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Weſel.</hi> There being arrived,<note place="margin">Duysburg</note> he found the chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters gone towares <hi>Duysburg,</hi> to a generall Synod, in which the Deputies of the Churches of four Dukedoms, <hi>viz. Gulick, Cleve, Berg and Mark</hi> were met, for which cauſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204906:20"/>he inſtantly went thither;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Duysburg</hi>
               </note> and had audience at their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the morning without delay, where having repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the ſum of his buſineſſe unto them, they Deputed ſix to receive the particular information, which was done in the afternoon; and they having made their report of that which then had been delivered unto them; they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to continne their conference the next day early by ſeven of the Clock with Maſter <hi>Dury,</hi> that they might bee able to relate the ſtate of the buſineſſe more fully, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July"/> to ground ſome reſolution thereupon: which being done accordingly, they reſolved <hi>that a Declaration ſhould be pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned inthe name of all their Churches, to bee givento Maſter</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>in approbation of his work, and that to this effect four of their Members whom they named ſhould draw it up; and being ſent to the Claſſes of all the Churches, and approved by them it ſhould be ſent to Maſter</hi> Dury <hi>under the ſeal of the Synod;</hi> which was alſo done afterward: this Reſolution being enacted the Synod was diſſolved;<note place="margin">Weſel</note> and Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did return to <hi>Weſel</hi> in the company of two of the Aſſembly who went home that way. At <hi>Weſel</hi> he ſaulted the chief Magiſtrate to move the Senate to concur with their Miniſtry; in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Reſolution taken at the Generall Synod, and went towards <hi>Cleve.</hi> At <hi>Cleve</hi> he ſtayed certain days, not to treat with any of the Divines,<note place="margin">Cleve</note> but to make acquaintance with the Governour who is Prince <hi>Mauriee</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> and with the Senators of that Dukedom. The Prince gave him publick audience in the Senate, where having briefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his bufineſs unto them; he delivered a <hi>Memorandum</hi> of his demands; which were theſe. <hi>Firſt, that as a State they would be pleaſed to declare their ſenſe of his buſineſs, as other States had done. Secondly, that they would authoriſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Divinity in the Acedemie of</hi> Duysburg <hi>to give their judgment of it. Thirdly, that Maſter</hi> Hundius <hi>the chief prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the place ſhould be commanded to claborate the task of fundamentall truths,</hi> which he had hitherto maintained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuits ſo well, that they had not been able to except hitherto any thing againſt them; and that task be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrought out, it ſhould by their order bee imparted to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204906:20"/>Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> for the furthering of his worke. <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Nimwegen</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe demands the anſwer was that they would firſt acquaint his Electorall Highneſs with them, and then let him know their anſwer, which they doubted not would bee approbatorie; having then conferred in private with ſome of the Councell, and agreed with the Vice Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor concerning the way of a future correſpondency, hee wentfrom thence, and on the tenth of <hi>July</hi> he came to <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegen.</hi> This City is a frontier of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> towards <hi>Germany;</hi> in it he ſaluted the Deputy of the Synod of <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who was well enclined to advance the Counſels of Peace towards the Churches of that Province, therefore Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did conſult with him concerning the way of furthering his work in the united Provinces: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July."/> His advice was that he ſhould inſtantly apply himſelf unto the Synods which then were convocated, which Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> took in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, not reſolving to follow it except emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent circumſtances ſhould move him thereunto,<note place="margin">Utrecht</note> and with this reſolution he went to <hi>Utrecht,</hi> where he ſtayed no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then was requiſite, to ſaulte the chief Preachers of his acquaintance, and the Profeſſors of the Univerfity, to let them know ſummarily the progreſſe of his work, and ſo came to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amſterdam</note> where having adviſed with Maſter <hi>Rulice</hi> concerning the way how to propoſe his work in thoſe Provinces, by him hee was induced to make his firſt application to the Synod of <hi>South-Holland,</hi> then aſſembled. at <hi>Dort;</hi> thither therefore he went, and acquainted the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod with his aim, but becauſe they were towards the end of their ordinary work,<note place="margin">Dort</note> and were loath to enter upon a new and extraordinary buſineſs, which might occaſion ſome debates amongſt them, they gave him a dilatorie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which made him perceive their unwillingneſſe to take the buſineſſe into conſideration; therefore hee went ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly from thence and came to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> on the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth.<note place="margin">Hardewick</note> Where having undeſtood that the Synod of <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was the next day to meet at <hi>Harderwick,</hi> hee went thither, and having made way by private addreſſes to bee heard in publick, the Synod gave him audience on the 23.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204906:21"/>and having propoſed the ſum of his buſineſs unto them,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
               </note> and deſired that ſom Deputies might be named to underſtand the particulars thereof to make a report unto the Synod; four were named to that effect, who met twice with him, and having fully perceived the grounds and progreſſe of his work, they made their report, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Auguſt."/> upon which the Synod after mature deliberation declared by the mouth of their Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>That they thanked him for imparting his buſineſſe unto them; that they highly approved the work, that they would join with their correſpondent Synods to ſurther it; that they would take the advice of their ſeverall Claſſes about it, and if need were would alſo confer with their ſupreme Magiſtrate concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; and that this their Declaration and Reſolution ſhould bee enacted: and the extract thereof given to Maſter</hi> Dury <hi>to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teſtifie ſo much on their behalf.</hi> For this reſolution Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Dury</hi> having thanked them, and gotten the extract in <hi>debita forma</hi> ratified, when hee had converſed in private with the chief of them hee went back again to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> where having ſtayed two days, he went to the <hi>Hague</hi> to learn the way how to apply himſelf unto the States, but finding no cleer way of addreſſe hee went to <hi>Leyden,</hi> and conferred with one of the Divinity Profeſſors Doctor <hi>Hornbeeck,</hi> the other two being out of the way; hee went back again to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Utrecht,</hi> to preinform the <hi>Claſſes</hi> of that Province, of his buſineſſe, that at their Synod which was to bee held in the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> they might com prepared to concur in his work. To this effect hee put papers in the hands of the Deputy of that Synod, to bee ſent unto all the <hi>Claſſes;</hi> and dealt with the Profſſors of Divinity of that Academy in the ſame way, to engage them to co-operate towards the ſame effect. This beeing done in the beginning of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſoon after the Synod of <hi>North-Holland</hi> was met as <hi>Alcmaer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alcmaer</note> he went thither, before the Synod was opened, that hee might prepare the Leading men to entertain his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but hee found after hee had dealt with the Preſes of the Synod, that debates ariſing amongſt themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the way of dealing with Maſter <hi>Dury;</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204906:21"/>miſſioners of the States who in all Synods are preſent at their meetings to countenance the ſame, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. Auguſt.</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Alomaer</hi>
               </note> did ſtop their proceeding, alledging that the ouſineſſe ought firſt to bee brought to the cogniſance of the States before the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſhould meddle therewith, thus beeing taken off, front making any further application to that Synod; hee w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt through <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> towards <hi>Leyden,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Hague.</hi> At <hi>Leyden</hi> hee imparted to the Divinity Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and to the French Miniſters,<note place="margin">Leyden</note> the papers which were requiſite for their information, to oblige them to join in the work with him; which hee found them willing to do. At the <hi>Hague</hi> having learned the way to make his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the States Generall: hee delivered unto their Aſſembly with a <hi>Memorandum</hi> (containing the ſubſtance of his buſineſs) ſeven bundles of papers each bundle inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to a Province for their informationconcerning his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.<note place="margin">Hague.</note> Upon the receit of theſe papers the States took the matter inſtantly into conſideration, and the next day the extract of their Reſolution was delivered unto Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> to this effect; that having received papers from him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the unity of Proteſtants, and conſidered his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they were reſolved to ſend the ſame unto each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Province, that there the buſineſſe might bee taken into conſideration:<note place="margin">Holland.</note> thus beeing referred unto the Severall Provinces, hee made it his work to deal by viſits and by letters, with the chief Leading men of <hi>Holland, Zealand, and Utrecht</hi> in Church and State, that when any publick meetings ſhould bee in any of theſe Provinces, they might bee furniſhed with matter to further his deſigne. Thus the time was imploied till the latter end of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> then in the beginning of <hi>September</hi> hee went to <hi>Utrecht,</hi> to bee at the Synod, which was to bee held there on the ſecond day of that moneth; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sept."/> there in one day he dealt with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors as a body, in the morning,<note place="margin">Utrecht</note> and had in the afternoon publick audience in the Synod, where his buſineſſe beeing examined by Deputies, a Reſolution was Declared to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his work, and to concur in it: whereupon (making all poſſible haſt to bee at the French Synod, which the next
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204906:22"/>day was to begin at <hi>Middelburg</hi> in <hi>Zealand</hi>) hee took his journey in the night towards <hi>Dort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durye</hi>'s being at <hi>Middelburg</hi>
               </note> and came on the fourth of <hi>September</hi> to <hi>Middelburg</hi> in the forenoon, where in one hours time he had the opportunity to ſalute the members of the French Synod at their riſing, and the <hi>Claſſes</hi> of the <hi>Iſle of Walcheren</hi> happlly met at the ſame time upon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie occaſion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Auguſt."/> At this <hi>Claſſes,</hi> hee propoſed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of coming to them, and deſired them to reſolve upon the moſt expeditious way of ſatisfactorie communication, which might bee uſed towards themſelvs and towards the other <hi>Claſſes</hi> of <hi>Zealand;</hi> becauſe before the end of that Moneth hee was to bee in <hi>Holland,</hi> to attend the Aſſembly of the States of that Province.</p>
            <p>At this motion they reſolved to meet again that day ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-night, to take his buſineſſe into conſideration, in the mean time they did appoint the Miniſtry of <hi>Middelburg</hi> to confer with Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> about the particulars whereof the Churches were to be informed, that when the <hi>Claſſes</hi> ſhould meet, they might bee able to make a report; and having determined the ſhorteſt times, within which the other <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> could ſucceſſively meet, to give Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> audience; they ordered their Scribe to write letters to each of them, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sept."/> to appoint them to meet at thoſe times to receive Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s propoſalls. Theſe things being thus ordered in the morning, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> in the afternoon had audience in the French Synod; where having briefly related his deſign, and the progreſſe thereof, and deſired that ſome ſhould bee De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to confer with him about particulars; they did appoint four of their chief members to meet with him; who having conferred twice with him, and underſtood the whole State of the buſineſſe, and made a report thereof unto the Synod; they reſolved to give him a Declaration of their judgment written in Latine, whereby their approbation of his work, their advice to carry it on, and their willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to concur therein ſhould be made apparent. No ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had the French made an end of conferring with him, but the Dutch Miniſters came together and invited him to their conſiſtorie; ſo from the one hee went to the other,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204906:22"/>and gave them the ſame information which the former had received, when hee had met twice with them.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Fliſhing</hi>
               </note> Theſe things beeing tranſacted at <hi>Middelburg,</hi> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went to <hi>Fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing,</hi> to make acquaintance with ſome men of note, who could contribute ſomwhat to the furthering of his deſign, with whom hee ſpent two days; and then came back to <hi>Middelburg,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sept."/> and conferred the third time with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of that City; to impart unto them the judgment of the French Synod, which the day before hee had received from their Preſes; and to reſolve ſom doubts, and incline ſome to a more full compliance then they ſeemed to bee bent unto. This beeing done in the morning;<note place="margin">Goes</note> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went the ſame day about night towards <hi>Goes;</hi> where the next morning hee met with the <hi>Claſſis</hi> which came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about his buſineſſe; and they having underſtood the ſtate thereof, and received the papers which he had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their information, and gotten a promiſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence from them,<note place="margin">Middolburg</note> hee returned to <hi>Middelburg</hi> the ſame day at night. Where the next day the States of <hi>Zealand</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come together, their Penſionary beeing much incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to further Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s deſign, did move to give him audience in their Aſſembly, where having opened ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the nature and progreſſe of his work unto them, they appointed one of every Colledge, with the Penſionarie or Secretary, to confer with him about particulars.</p>
            <p>On the day following, which was the 11, the <hi>Claſſis</hi> of <hi>Walcheren,</hi> as they had appointed the week before, met in the morning; and when the Miniſtry of <hi>Middelburg</hi> had made their report, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> was called into the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, where Maſter <hi>Appollonius</hi> was choſen Preſes, who in the name of the <hi>Claſſis</hi> thanked him for acquainting them with the progreſs of his work, for which they praiſed God; and ſeeing they had been deſired by him to propoſe all the doubts which might ariſe in their minds about this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to hear what could be ſaid for the removing of them; therefore they had gathered together the heads of doubtful matters, and were willing to propoſe them, to underſtand
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204906:23"/>how they ſhould bee reſolved: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. Sept.</label> and when Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had ſhewed a willingneſſe to confer with them about thoſe matters,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Middelburg</hi>
               </note> Maſter <hi>Appollonius</hi> by way of queſtion, propoſed the doubts out of a paper, to which when Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had given his anſwers, and continued in conference with him above two hours and a halfe; hee left off making further enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> deſired of them if they were ſatisſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they would impart unto him their judgment as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had done in writing; and if they intended to concur in the work, that they would appoint ſome to correſpond with him in their name for future communication. Having made theſe motions, hee went out, that they might conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by themſelvs what to anſwer. And beeing called in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>They did thank him for the pains taken in anſwering their doubts, declaring themſelvs ſatisfied thereby, and that they would give him their written Declaration to make known their aſſent to his worck. And that they had named two of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to correſpond with him for a concurrence.</hi> For this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having thanked them hee took his leav of the Aſſembly; and in the evening about ſix of the Clock, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> being ſent for to meet with the Deputies of the States appointed to confer with him; hee went to them and ſtayed with them till eight, diſcourſing of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar paſſages of his Negotiation, and giving unto them the copies of certain writings which they compared with the originalls. At parting they promiſed to make their report, and Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> delivered a <hi>Memorandum</hi> unto them to be preſented in his name to the States, wherein hee deſired; Firſt, that they would recommend the work unto their Churches. Secondly, that they would declare their own ſenſe of it, as other States had done. Thirdly, that they would further the enterpriſ towards the other Provinces in the Aſſembly of the Generall States. Two days were ſpent after this at <hi>Middelburg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bergen on the Zoom.</note> and then Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went to <hi>Bergen on the Zoom:</hi> where hee expected to meet the <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> convocated, but ſome neglect beeing fallen out in the conveyance of the letter which was ſent from <hi>Middelburg</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:204906:23"/>to give them warning of the time of Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s arrivall,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Utrecht</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. Septe.</label> they came not: Therefore Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> got the Miniſtry of <hi>Bergen on the Zoom</hi> to meet, and to them hee delivered the information which the <hi>Claſſis</hi> ſhould have had if it had met, intreating them at their next ordinarie meeting, which was to bee in <hi>October,</hi> to impart it unto them, which they promiſed to do, and Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> having ſaluted the chief Magiſtrates of the place, went the next day to <hi>Zirickzee,</hi> where he found the <hi>Claſſis</hi> met at the time appointed; and having conferred with them, and acquainted them with all proceedings, they promiſed their concurrence with the other Churches to further the work.</p>
            <p>Having made an end with the Churches of <hi>Zealand,</hi> hee returned to <hi>Dort,</hi> and from thence to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht;</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received the Act of the Synod of that Province, and the Declaratiou of the Profeſſors of Divinity, hee begun to make ſom acquaintance with ſome of the States of <hi>Utrecht</hi> to prepare a way for a future application, and hearing that the meeting of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> was drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an end, hee went to the <hi>Hague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hague.</note> and there having repreſented to the States his buſineſſe, and deſired them to depute ſom to conſider of pauticulars as the States of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had done; hee received on the firſt of <hi>October</hi> this anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the States of</hi> Holland <hi>wiſhed all good ſucceſs to Maſter</hi> Dury's <hi>endeavours in the work hee had in hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they found it not yet expedient for them to enter upon the particular conſideration of that work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That when they ſhould underſtand how far the</hi> Lutherans <hi>were willing to concur in it, then they would not bee wanting to further it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this anſwer Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> finding that their dilatorie reſolutions did proceed from a miſtruſt of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination; for the want of information how far the chief of them were ingaged, he reſolved to cauſe print ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204906:24"/>of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> party to remove this obſtacle: <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </note> and to that effect gave to a Printer in the <hi>Hague, Firſt, a Declaration of the Saxon Divines, in a Conferrence held at</hi> Leipzich <hi>concerning their agreement with us. Secondly, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Protestant States at their Aſſembly held at</hi> Frankfort, <hi>wherin they allow of that conferrence, and Declare their reſolution to advance the agreement. Thirdly, a Letter written to the King of Sweden by one of his chief Biſhops, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to advance this deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee ſpoke alſo to the Reſidents of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to move them to co-operate in removing this obſtacle, either by procuring ſome Commiſſion from their Maſters to that effect, or by private conferrences with ſome of the States, to let them ſee, that on the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſide would bee no averſion from the work, when the way of tranſacting matters ſhould bee duely prepared: this laſt both of them promiſed to do, and concerning the firſt they promiſed to acquaint their reſpective Maſters with Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s motion.<note place="margin">Utrecht</note> Thus having made an end with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> he returned to <hi>Utrecht,</hi> where he addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto the ordinary Deputies of the States of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, becauſe it was uncertain when the States themſelves would have any meeting. Theſe knowing by the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the States Generall, and by the Declaration of their Divines of the Academy, and the Act of their Provinciall Synod the nature of the work; appointed without delay three Commiſſioners, to confer with Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing particular matters, which when they had done and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo made their report, an Act was drawn up in the name of theſe Deputies, declaring fully <hi>their approbation of the work; thanking Maſter</hi> Dury <hi>for his pains in it; and promiſing their ready concurrence to further it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leyden.</note> and as an act of State was delivered unto him. From thence beeing gone to <hi>Leyden,</hi> hee got the Divinity profeſſors to meet as a faculty, and reſolve (upon the information which they then fully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) to give him their judgment approbatorie of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking in writing. And whiles they were about doing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204906:24"/>this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. Octob.</label> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Hague</hi>
               </note> hee took that time to viſit the Leading men of the French Churches at <hi>Dort, Rotterdam, Delft, and the Hague;</hi> from whence beeing returned to <hi>Leyden</hi> on the 24 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> hee received the judgment of the Proſeſſors of that Univerſitie; commending his endeavours; approving ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the deſigne; giving their advice in it, and promiſing freely their concurrence to advance the effect thereof. When hee had dealt thus far with the States, Churches, and Univerſities of <hi>Holland, Zealand, and Utrecht,</hi> hee was encouraged by ſome of the States Generall, to make a ſecond application unto their Colledge, that they ſhould declare their approbation of his work in a publick way. But the anſwer on the 29, was to refer him to the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Provinces, with a promiſe of Recommending his deſign unto them. Whereupon hee found himſelf obliged to go the Circuit of the other four Provinces, to gain their aſſent to his undertaking; and to inform their Churches and Academies of the circumſtances of his Negotiation; as he had informed thoſe with whom hee had formerly dealt; So then on the 2 of <hi>November</hi> hee went from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> towards <hi>Frieſland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Frieſland</note> where hee dealt firſt with the Divinity Profeſſors of <hi>Franeker;</hi> then with the Deputies of the States of <hi>Frieſland</hi> met at <hi>Lewarden;</hi> with the Deputies of the Synod of that Province, to addreſſe the information requiſite to bee given to all their <hi>Claſſes:</hi> and laſtly, with Prince <hi>William</hi> the Governour of the Province; by whom, as by all the reſt, the deſigne was approved, and a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy willingneſſe declared to help towards the advancement of it.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Lewarden</hi> hee went to <hi>Groningen,</hi> where proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame Method and way towards the Deputies of the States, towards the Profeſſors of the Univerſity,<note place="margin">Groningen</note> and towards the Deputy of the Synod for the information of the <hi>Claſſes,</hi> he found the ſame acceptance of his work, and received the Declarations requiſite to evidence the ſame. From <hi>Groningen</hi> hee went to <hi>Swoll</hi> in the Province of <hi>Over-yſſel;</hi> there although hee found the Province ſo di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204906:25"/>within it ſelf,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Over-Yſſel</hi>
               </note> that there was no meeting of Deputies to eprelent as elſewhere the Souveraignty of that Province, yet it fell happily out that there was an extraordinary meeting of the Deputies of the chief City at <hi>Swoll</hi> about the time when he was there;<note place="margin">Swoll</note> to theſe having made his appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Novem."/> and gotten ſeverally their promiſe to further the work in their quarters; and having alſo dealt with the Miniſtry of that Diſtrict at an extraordinary <hi>Claſſis</hi> which then was called, and with the Deputie of the Synod for the information of the other <hi>Claſſes</hi> of the Province;<note place="margin">Deventer</note> he went to <hi>Deventer,</hi> where hee conferred with two of the chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrers for the ſpace of an hour onely; and then ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards <hi>Arnhem,</hi> where the Court of the Dukedom of <hi>Gelderland</hi> reſides. There the Senators of that Court ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been preinformed of Maſter <hi>Dury</hi>'s deſigne (by their Commiſſioners,<note place="margin">Arnhem</note> who had been at the Synod of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in <hi>July</hi>) were ready to further his work, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay gave him an act of approbation concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus all the Provinces, Churches, and Academies of the united Provinces were dealt withall, and the buſineſſe bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accepted and imbraced by all, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſet himſelf to give information of this ſucceſs to all his correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in forraign Churches where hee had been Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before; and to this effect hee remained conſtantly at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> for the conveniency of ſending letters to all quarters; in which imploiment hee continued from the middle of <hi>December</hi> till the end of <hi>January,</hi> in the year 1657; in which time two things fell out, much tending to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of his work;<note place="margin">Amſterdam</note> the one was, that by the means of the Miniſtry of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the obſtruction which was put unto his Negotiation towards the Churches of <hi>South-Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and North-Holland</hi> in their two Synods, was removed by the opening of a door of communication with them in time to come which theſe of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> did undertake to procure by their <hi>Claſſis</hi> and correſpondency with the other Churches of the Province. The other was that the Prince of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204906:25"/>
               <hi>Sweden</hi> beeing come to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dury</hi>'s being at <hi>Amſterdam</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1656. Januar.</label> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him, and having informed him of the progreſs of his work, and how far matters were prepared on the ſide of the reformed party, the Prince declared his reſolution that hee would move the King his brother to ſet ſome <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> Miniſter a work, who ſhould prepare the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches by going amongſt them, as Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Reformed, that when Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> ſhould come afterward unto them; for the matter of reconcilement he might find them willing and fitted to entertain his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. to confirm the Prince in this reſolution Maſter <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> dealt afterward with his Secretary and gave him a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandum,</hi> intimating the way by which it might bee effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, with much credit to the Church of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any offence to the other <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>When all matters were diſpatched at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went to take his paſſage for <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> where whiles hee did ſtay for a wind, a <hi>Claſſis</hi> was held, wherein his buſineſſe was propoſed, but could not at that time bee taken into conſideration, the <hi>Claſſis</hi> beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocated for another end; therefore it was referred to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meeting appointed at a certain time for that end; in the mean time the wind continuing croſe, Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> went to <hi>Zealand,</hi> hoping for a readierpaſſage from thence;<note place="margin">Rotterdam</note> then was likely to fall at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> chiefly becauſe hee thought hee might bee able in the interim of his abode, to further his deſigne by ripening the reſolution of the States of <hi>Zealand</hi> to appear therein; which in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was effected; for before hee came from thence; the States did write an order to their ſeverall <hi>Claſſes</hi> to give in their advices concerning his bufineſſe,<note place="margin">In <hi>Zealand</hi>
               </note> with the reaſons which move them to approve of the deſigne; to the end that having underſtood the advice and motives of their Churches, they might have a better ground to appear in the work as a State. This Maſter <hi>Dury</hi> did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand from the Penſionarie, and from the Secretary of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204906:26"/>the States of that Province;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Durye</hi>'s being at</note> and not long after, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno. </seg>1657. Febru.</label> the wind turning fair, he went from <hi>Fliſhing</hi> on the 14 of <hi>February,</hi> and landed at <hi>Marget</hi> on the day following. From whence hee came up directly for <hi>London,</hi> in the company of a publick Miniſter of State, from one of the Electors of the Empire, who makes his application to his Highneſs the Lord Protector.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:204906:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
